Okay, we resume today דף כ"ג עמוד ב', Daf Chaf Gimmel Amud
Bais, the דף Daf is דף כ"ד, Daf Chaf Daled, but we
pick up a few, about ten lines at the before דף כ"ג
עמוד ב', Daf Chaf Gimmel Amud Bais, יושב. Yoshev. One of the
people who or are one of the ways in which the עבודה
Avoda becomes invalidated is if a person is sitting at the time
of the עבודה. Avoda. So the question is going to be what's
the basis for this? מנלן, Minalan, where do we know this from?
אמר רבא אמר רב, Amar Rava Amar Rav, אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Nachman, אמר קרא, Amar Kra,
the verse says, לעמוד לשרת. La'amod Lishareis.
It says to stand to serve. So, כי בו בחר ה' אלהיך
מכל שבטיך לעמוד Ki vo vachar Hashem elokecha mikol shevatcha la'amod through
him the נביאים, Nevi'im, God has chosen the נביאים, Nevi'im, excuse me,
the כהנים, Kohanim,
God has chosen the כהנים Kohanim from all of the tribes or
the לויים, Levi'im, but okay here read as the כהנים Kohanim from
all of the tribes to stand to serve before God. Okay, לעמוד
לשרת. La'amod Lishareis. לעמידה בחרתיו ולא לישיבה. La'amida bechartiv velo leyoshiva.
I have chosen him when he is standing, not when he is
sitting. So meaning that the, now it's a funny phrase of בחרתיו,
bechartiv, כי בו בחר ה' אלהיך, ki vo vachar Hashem elokecha, it
could have said אין שירות אלא בעמידה. Ein sheirus ela be'amida. The
proper way of doing the service is by standing, not by sitting.
But by framing it as like his chosenness is dependent on this,
that's going to allow the גמרא Gemara to ask the next question.
So let's take a look at the גמרא's Gemara question. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. So the rabbis asked, לעמוד לשרת La'amod Lishareis מצוה. mitzvah.
If it had just said לעמוד לשרת La'amod Lishareis I would have
thought that's just a מצוה mitzvah that you're supposed to do it
standing. כשהוא אומר Keshu'omer when it says העומדים, Ha'omdim, העומדים שם לפני
ה', Ha'omdim sham lifnei Hashem, who
that stand there, שנה עליו הכתוב לעכב. shana alav hakesuv le'akev. So
this is a general principle by קדשים Kadshim which we haven't always,
you know, should have, you know,
have responded, you know, employed. תוספות Tosfos asks sometimes why the גמרא
Gemara seems, you know, seems sometimes to pay attention to this and
sometimes not. But the general principle is that unless the פסוק pasuk
repeats it, it's not seen as an absolute requirement. It's seen as
a לכתחילה l'chatchila not as a בדיעבד. b'dieved. But because it says
twice and also says העומדים שם, Ha'omdim sham, that tells you that
even בדיעבד b'dieved if it's not done it is not good. Okay,
ושרת ככל אחיו הלוים, Veshares kechol echav halevi'im, he will serve העומדים
שם. ha'omdim sham. Okay, it's actually a previous פסוק. pasuk. Now, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
לויים Levi'im have to be standing?
I know, I said a minute ago that the פשט p'shat of
the פסוקים psukim is לויים, Levi'im, but the גמרא Gemara often לויים
Levi'im refer to the כהנים, Kohanim, certainly the way חז"ל Chazal read
it. Okay, now, אמרי רבא לרב נחמן, amrei Rava leRav Nachman, said
רבא Rava to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, מכדי, michdi, one minute, let's
take a look. יושב כזר דמי. Yoshev kezari dami. If you're sitting,
you're like a non-כהן. Kohen. Now where does he get that idea?
So where he gets that idea is because we chose to read
the פסוק pasuk not just אין שירות אלא בעמידה, Ein sheirus ela
be'amida,
but we chose to read the פסוק pasuk which is לעמידה בחרתיו.
La'amida bechartiv. בו בחר ה' אלהיך. Bo vachar Hashem elokecha.
He is chosen when he is לעמוד לשרת. la'amod lishares. When not,
he's not part of the chosen tribe or the this tribe chosen
within the chosen tribe, the chosen tribe of the chosen people. So
he's not of the chosen nature when he is not standing. So
that means he's like a non-כהן. Kohen. Okay, well if he's like
a non-כהן, Kohen, so why don't we say, since he's כזר דמי
kezari dami and מחל עבודה mechal avoda and from there we infer
that he invalidates the עבודה, Avoda, let's draw the other consequence. Let's
say, אימא מה זר במיתה אף יושב במיתה. Eima mazari b'misa af
yoshev b'misa. He is deserving
of the divine מיתה misa death penalty. How do you know not
to take it that far? That's the question. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אלמה תניא, Alama tanya, now maybe you would say yes that
is true, but no, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, אבל ערל
אונן יושב, Aval arel, onen, yoshev,
so that's true if a non-כהן Kohen does the עבודה Avoda or
if we're going to see somebody without washed hands or somebody, you
know, who doesn't have all the בגדים bigadim on them or is
drunk, they are חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Okay, a number of those
places says explicitly, right? Like by the drunk case it says by,
you know, it says by בני אהרן, Bnei Aharon, right, יין ושכר
אל תשת, Yayin v'sheichar al tesht, you know, ולא תמותו. v'lo samusu.
So those three are people get מיתה, misa, a divine death, if
they do the service that way. But an ערל, arel, an uncircumcised
כהן, Kohen, or an אונן, onen, somebody who just suffered, you know,
an immediate relative just died, יושב yoshev or somebody who's sitting, אינם
במיתה אלא באזהרה. einam b'misa ela b'azhara. They don't get the divine
מיתה misa death penalty, they do invalidate the service, but they only
transgress a negative prohibition. So why is that? Why don't we say
that he's not chosen, he's like a זר? zar? So the גמרא
Gemara says, משום דהוי מחוסר בגדים ושלא רחץ ידים ורגלים שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד. Mishum dehavi mechusar begadim v'shelo rachatz yadayim v'raglayim shenei kesuvim
ba'im k'echad.
Because the categories of people other than a זר zar that get
מיתה misa are somebody who is not have all the בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehuna and somebody does not or somebody who is not washed
hands and feet, and those are two
explicit cases and therefore they are the exceptions, not the rule, and
you can't therefore generalize. שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין, shenei kesuvim
ba'im k'echad ein malm'din, and whenever that's true, you cannot sort of
more generalize and apply it to other cases. Now, רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosfos both ask that the גמרא Gemara never said that we
needed to infer it from those other cases. If I needed to
infer it from the guy who from the כהן Kohen who was
not wearing the בגדים, bigadim, I could say I can't infer it
from it because there are two פסוקים psukim that make them an
exception, not a rule, and I can't generalize. But I'm not asking
to... generalize. I'm asking to say that if he's not standing, it's
like he's a non-כהן, Kohen, he's like a זר. Zar. So I
don't have to generalize from there. Fine, I'm not gonna learn from
there. But I'm just gonna learn from the fact that this puts
him in the זר Zar category. Okay, so תוספות Tosfos says, so
that's, so רש"י Rashi sort of struggles with that. תוספות, Tosfos, the
way תוספות Tosfos explains the גמרא, Gemara, which he sort of admits
is not exactly פשט, Pshat, but the way he explains the גמרא
Gemara is the following: is that if you remember,
the גמרא Gemara also said by בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehuna, כשאין בגדיהם
עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם. Keshein bigdeihem aleihem ein kehunatam aleihem. When they're
not wearing the בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehuna, they're not real כהנים. Kohanim.
So תוספות Tosfos reads the גמרא, Gemara, if even so we needed
to learn from a פסוק Pasuk that without wearing the בגדים, Begadim,
because it says by the מכנסיים, Michnasayim, it says that if you're
not wearing the מכנסיים ולא תשאו עון, Michnasayim velo sismusu, so if
even there it had to say explicitly you get the death penalty,
and we couldn't just say, oh, you're like a זר, Zar, you
get the death penalty. So you see, like Michael said, let's not
take the comparison too far. Okay. So fine, by the כהן Kohen
who's not wearing the בגדים Begadim or by the כהן Kohen who
is, you know, not washed the hands, there it explicitly says death
penalty. But where it doesn't explicitly say death penalty, even if we
say he's like a זר, Zar, we're not gonna be overly literal,
okay? So that's why we're going to say that here, it's not
going to, it's going to invalidate, but we're not going to be
overly literal to say you get the death penalty. So the גמרא
Gemara says: ולמאן דאמר מלמדין, U-le-man de-amar melamdin, and if you say
that actually you can generalize, שתויי יין הוי ליה שלישי, Shtu'ei yayin
havei lei shelishi,
the case about being drunk as I said before, that's by, you
know, אחרי מות שני בני אהרן Acharei mos shenei venei Aharon or
whatever, actually, no, that's not at the beginning of אחרי מות. Acharei
mos. Anyway, it's יין ושכר Yayin ve-shechar right after they die, it
says anyway, יין ושכר אל תשת אתה ובניך אתך בבאכם Yayin ve-shechar
al taysht atah u-vanecha itacha be-vo'achem whatever, ולא תמותו. Ve-lo samutu. So
that's the third פסוק. Pasuk. ושלשה דברי הכל מלמדין. Ve-sheloshah divrei hakol
melamdin.
So anyway, here are three times, the way תוספות Tosfos reads this.
Again, it's a little bit not, not exactly the פשט Pshat of
the words, but anyway, the way תוספות Tosfos reads it is, since
here the תורה Torah said it explicitly, we're going to work with
the assumption that it's not enough to say you're like a זר.
Zar. Unless the תורה Torah explicitly says you get the death penalty,
we're, we're, we can, we're going to say you're enough like a
זר Zar that you invalidate the עבודה, Avodah, but not enough that
you're deserving like divine death. Again, this is all divine death. Okay,
so bottom line is, when a person is not standing, they're not
seen as being either that's not good שירות, Sheirus, אין שירות אלא
בעמידה Ein sheirus ela be-amidah is a more modest way of saying
it, okay, that service is standing, they only they also serve who
only stand and wait. Okay, but or, anyway, anybody get the reference?
Yes. Okay, anyway, or, but or the way the גמרא Gemara is
saying it is you're not even like the chosen tribe in that
capacity, and but nevertheless, don't take that too literal. You're not a
real זר, Zar, you don't get מיתה. Misa. Yeah, Michael, question?
Yeah. So, can't we say that that's only from the point where
you need a כהן? Kohen? Like let's say it was שחיטה. Shechitah.
That's like no long כהן.
Kohen. Yeah. Um, so that is true, and the opening משנה Mishna
of the second פרק Perek started with קבלת הדם, Kabbalas Hadam, right?
Is that, I believe correct. Let's go all the way to the
beginning. כל הזבחים שקבלו דמם זר אונן טבול יום וכו׳ Kol hazvachim
shekiblu damam zar onen tevul yom etc. Okay, so the question you
ask the right question, which is, is that how many of these
things are a problem with שחיטה? Shechitah? Because שחיטה Shechitah could be
a זר, Zar, maybe all these things you get a pass by?
You so we have not, you know, we haven't addressed that question,
but yes, the whole conversation is only from קבלה Kabbalah and onwards,
which is a מצות כהונה.
Mitzvas Kehuna. So at least at this point, or I don't know,
maybe some point other point we'll answer it, you could be sitting
and do the שחיטה.
Shechitah. Presumably. I mean, I don't know, I'd have to check offhand
if that's correct, but yes, presumably. Okay, we certainly have not said
otherwise. Okay. עמד על גבי כלים. Amad al gabei keilim. Now we
get to interesting scenarios that are in the משנה. Mishna. If a
כהן Kohen is standing on top of a vessel, like an upturned,
you know, pot or something, על גבי בהמה, Al gabei behemah, or
there are a lot of animals roaming around there, if he's got
his foot on top of an animal's foot, or, you know, or
על גבי רגלי חבירו, Al gabei raglei chaveiro, or he's standing on
his friend's foot, פסול, Pasul, it's invalid. All these are invalid.
So the גמרא Gemara says... what if he's wearing shoes?
Oh, that's definitely invalid. You have to be barefoot. That is correct.
מנהלן? Minalan? How do you know? That's a good question. You're right.
I mean, it makes it sound like it's a, it's a very
good question. It makes it sound like it's what defines standing as
opposed to the real point that's being made by this משנה, Mishna,
which is that there can't be a חציצה Chatzitzah between his foot
and the ground. It's a good question, you're right. Like, you know,
but I, maybe it just takes it for granted that we know
that the כהנים Kohanim do it barefoot and so on. But, yeah,
מנהלן? Minalan? Now, where do you get this from? Because, right, why
is this not standing? How do you know that you need the
idea of your skin touching the ground, which is the implicit point
of this משנה? Mishna? Actually, wearing shoes could also be a problem
with ייתור בגדים Yittur begadim and so on. Anyway, דתני, De-tani, we
taught, דבי רבי ישמעאל, De-bei Rabbi Yishmael, הוא הרצפה מקדשת וכלי שרת
מקדשים. Hu haritzpah mekadeshet ve-khlei shareis mekadeshim. Now, there's a very important
question about what the גירסא Girsa is here in the גמרא. Gemara.
Is it מקדשת Mekadeshet or מקודשת? Mekudeshet? Okay. Is it that the
floor is,
let's first read it מקודשת. Mekudeshet. The floor has been sanctified, and
the holy vessels have been sanctified. מקדשת Mekadeshet means sanctifies something else.
So first I'm going to read it as...
Oh, so it'd be מקודשים, Mekudashim, is that what it would be,
מקודשים? Mekudashim? What? If it's all that it's sanctified, right?
Then כלי שרת מקודשים. Klei shareis mekudashim. Right. Not מקדשין. mikadshin. Right.
Not מקדשין. mikadshin. So I'm going to read it first מקודשת mikudeshet
and מקודשים. mikudashim. Okay. So the same way the floor has been
sanctified and the holy vessels have been sanctified, let's say, you know,
the bowl that you catch the blood in, okay, this is the
way רש״י Rashi seems to read it, then I'll read it מקדשת,
mikadeshet, which is the way תוספות Tosafot seems to read it. מה
כלי שרת, ma klei shares, so מה כלי שרת לא יהא דבר
חוצץ בינו לבין כלי שרת, ma klei shares lo yehei davar chotzetz
beino l'vein klei shares, the same way when the כהן kohen holds
the כלי שרת, klei shares, right, the holy vessel to catch the
blood. So it says he has to, it says ולקח הכהן, velakach
hakohen, לקיחה בעצמו של כהן lekicha be'itzmo shel kohen
is the way we read, he has to take it directly without
anything in between, he has to directly handle the holy vessel, you
know, so he has to directly handle it.
So where were we? מה כלי שרת לא יהא דבר חוצץ בינו
לבין כלי שרת אף רצפה לא יהא דבר חוצץ בינו לבין הרצפה.
ma klei shares lo yehei davar chotzetz beino l'vein klei shares af
ritzpa lo yehei davar chotzetz beino l'vein haritzpa. So similarly when he
touches there shouldn't be anything between him and the floor. Now what
exactly is the comparison, right? I mean so the comparison seems to
be that the כהן kohen has to be directly if you sort
of think about these things as, I don't know, like electricity and
he is a conductor, you know, whatever. Anyway you got the floor
down there is holy, you got the כלי שרת klei shares he's
holding here is holy. So the same way everything has to be,
all the sort of things have to be the holy things have
to be directly in contact with the כהן. kohen. The same way
here it says ולקח הכהן velakach hakohen we say לקיחה בעצמו של
כהן, lekicha be'itzmo shel kohen,
the כהן kohen directly with his hands and not with anything in
between has to do the taking which means he has to hold
the vessels and hold, you know, hold the כלי שרת. klei shares.
So his need to stand on the floor means he's got to
stand directly on the floor. What we learned from the כלי שרת
klei shares is he has to be directly in contact with the
holy things. So the same way his hands have to be directly
in contact with it, his feet have to be directly in contact
with the floor which is also the holy things. That's the way
רש״י Rashi reads it. Now תוספות Tosafot reads it in a, I
think, more interesting way which is also the פשט pshat of our
גירסא girsa which is מקדשת, mikadeshet, sanctifies. Okay. But here's the problem
then. Now what does it mean to sanctify? So let's start with
the כלי שרת. klei shares. There's a general idea for example that
when I take, you know, Michael comes ahead and he brings his
מנחה, mincha, let's start with that, okay, and which he made at
home in his, you know, in his pot, whatever, in his pan.
I the כהן kohen I'm going to take it and put it
into this כלי שרת, klei shares, the קמיצה, kmitza, okay. That act
of putting it in the כלי שרת klei shares actually sanctifies, brings
the קמיצה kmitza to a higher level of sanctity. Okay. Or for
example the גמרא Gemara says when you שחט shacht a בהמה, behema,
the knife which is a כלי שרת klei shares somehow does a
higher degree of sanctifying the blood and brings it to a level
where now it could be brought up to the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So
when these various sort of, you know, sort of objects materials come
in contact with the כלי שרת klei shares in the context of
עבודה, avoda, they get elevated and raised to a level the גמרא
Gemara actually says, you know, when I sanctify my animal it's only
קדושת פה, kedushat peh, it's only a sanctity that comes, like, through
my words. But when it comes into, you know, contact with a
כלי שרת klei shares it gets elevated to a more level that
sort of cannot be transferred and so on. So it raises the
level of sanctity. That's the idea of מקדשת, mikadeshet, מקדשת, mikadeshet, it
sanctifies. Okay. So that's great. Now we understand what כלי שרת מקדשת
klei shares mikadeshet means. The logical problem is that's because it has
to elevate the level of the things that are going to be
put on the מזבח mizbe'ach and therefore it comes, it has to
come directly in contact. So when it says כלי שרת לא יהא
דבר חוצץ, klei shares lo yehei davar chotzetz, it means for example
there can't be any dirt, let's say, in the bowl that I
catch the blood in. There can't be a חציצה. chatzitza. Okay, because
it has to come directly in contact with the blood. What does
it have to do with my feet touching the floor? Right? That's
not an analogy. And even if you say that somehow I need
the floor to sanctify me the כהן kohen to make me fit
to do the עבודה, avoda, which might be true, it is true
actually we're going to say that in a minute. But it's not
analogous. Just because it has to sanctify the blood I can't learn
from that that it has to sanctify me, right? You know, how
does one imply the other? You got the question? So therefore תוספות
Tosafot says based on this read that כלי שרת klei shares here
does not mean the bowl. כלי שרת klei shares means the בגדי
כהונה. bigdei kehuna. Sometimes we use the word כלי שרת klei shares
to refer to the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna and here's what it's
saying.
Where, where else do we see it?
He quotes one or two cases we actually do. So not usually.
So what תוספות Tosafot says is the following. Remember we just learned
a week ago or so that there can't be any, you know,
anything between my skin and the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. There can't
be a חציצה. chatzitza. Remember all those discussions? So the חציצה chatzitza
between the כלי שרת klei shares is not the bowl and the
blood. It's between my here tunic and my skin. Okay. And why
can't there be? Because part of what we're going to say now
is wearing the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna sanctifies me. It makes me
a כהן kohen fit to serve in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
like we say אין כהונתם עליהם אין בגדיהם עליהם. ein kehunatam aleihem
ein bigdeihem aleihem. So the same way we have an idea that
wearing the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna coming in contact with this stuff
that's part of the apparatus of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash sanctified,
makes, you know, raises my level and makes me fit to serve
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Guess what else does? My skin
directly coming in contact with the floor of the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. That also makes me like a part of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and fits to do the עבודה Avodah in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And I really love this idea because, you know,
it fits to the whole way the תורה Torah speaks about, right?
The way the כהנים Kohanim were initially sanctified or initiated to do
the עבודה Avodah in the, you know, in the seven days of
the מילואים, Miluim, that the exact same thing about putting the anointing
oil on all of the, you know, on all of the, what
do you call it? On all of the vessels of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and of the structure of the or the משכן
Mishkan was also the way it was put on the כהנים. Kohanim.
Right? And the גמרא Gemara actually made a lot of comparisons there,
you know the point אין בגדיהם עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם. ein bigdeihem
aleihem ein kehunasam aleihem. So the בגדים bigadim sanctify, but the כהנים
Kohanim themselves are transformed. Part of the process there was to transform
the כהנים Kohanim and make them like part of the objects, like
when we talk about the רבנות, Rabbanut, we talk about the כלי
קודש. Klei Kodesh. Make them the actual objects of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Of course the point is, you know, they gotta live
their lives too. They're human beings, they're not inanimate objects. It's not
like they go around being כלי קודש. Klei Kodesh. Right? I'm with
a rabbi, when do you get your personal life? Right? You're always...
so the point is, okay, when you enter the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and whatever you do, the washings or whatever you prepare yourself,
and then your feet touch the floor and your body wears the
clothes, then you're transformed and then you're sanctified and then you're part
of the מקדש Mikdash to do the עבודה. Avodah. Okay, so that's
the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, which is a very lovely reading.
You just have to, all you have to do is stretch the
meaning of the word כלי שרת klei sharet to mean the בגדי
כהונה. bigdei kehuna.
Can the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna be a חציצה chatzitza between the
כלי שרת klei sharet and...
no. No, so there is that still that other הלכה halacha that
you have to do הליכה בצימי halichah bitzimi or whatever...
meaning it would be a חציצה. chatzitza.
It would be a חציצה. chatzitza. Right. It would be a problem.
And so let's say you were stepping on בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna
for a second and, you know, you're not...
yeah, that would be a problem. That would be a problem. I
mean, again, it's interesting that it doesn't mention that.
But presumably if you're stepping on yourself, you put one leg on
top of the other?
Well, yes, but for a different reason. So let's take a look.
Okay, that will come up too. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. וצריכא, u’tzricha, now the משנה Mishna had to tell
me all three scenarios of a vessel, an animal, and my friend's
foot. וצריכא, u’tzricha, דאי אשמעינן כלי משום דלאו מינא דבשר נינהו de’ee
ashmeinan kli mishum delav mina d’basar ninhu
because it's not flesh, so that certainly would be something extraneous and
a חציצה. chatzitza. אבל בהמה דמינא דבשר הוא, aval behema de’mina d’basar
hu, but an animal which is something, you know, it's flesh, אימא
לא, eima lo, maybe it's not a חציצה, chatzitza, it's like מין
במין. min b’min. ואי אשמעינן בהמה דלאו מינא דאדם הוא, v’ee ashmeinan
behema delav mina d’adam hu,
because that's not a person, like flesh of a person, it's not
from the same category, it's not a real מין במין. min b’min.
אבל חבירו דאדם הוא, aval chaveiro d’adam hu,
but my friend who's another human being, so it's like a מין
במין min b’min and it's not a חציצה, chatzitza, אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe it wouldn't be a problem. צריכא. tzricha. Now it doesn't
tell me then why it says why I don't say that. Okay,
that is a question. When do we say מין במין min b’min
is חוצץ chotzetz or not חוצץ? chotzetz? Maybe at the end of
the day what we're saying is that's still not מינו. mino. It
said "chaveiro" though, right? He said "chaveiro". Well, that's still not, and
yes, that's true, but fine, obviously the משנה Mishna could have jumped
to the end case, but it wanted to build up to it.
Okay, but it is interesting like why, you know, why don't we
say it's not מין במין, min b’min, maybe because at the end
of the day every human being is distinct. There's never a מינו.
mino. There, good lesson about that. Okay, תניא, Tanya, now what about
Michael? Presumably if you stand on your own foot, though, you would
say that that is considered מין במין min b’min and not a
חציצה. chatzitza. The fact that the משנה Mishna mentioned חבירו, chaveiro, it
should have said אפילו ברגל עצמו. afilu b’regel atzmo. It didn't say
that. So implicitly the answer is that that's not a problem at
all. That's correct, because of a מין במין min b’min reason and
there's another good reason as well, which we'll see in a minute.
תניא, Tanya, we taught a ברייתא, Baraisa, רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer
omer: רגל אחת על הכלי ורגל אחת על הרצפה. Regel achat al
hakli v’regel achat al haritzpa.
One foot is on the ground and one foot is on the
is on like, you know, a pot. רגל אחת על האבן ורגל
אחת על הרצפה. Regel achat al ha’even v’regel achat al haritzpa. One
foot is on a stone that's not attached to the ground and
one is on the ground. רואין, Roin, so you take a look.
You assess the situation. כל שאילו ינטל הכלי וינטל האבן kol she’illu
yinnatel hakli v’yinnatel ha’even יכול לעמוד על רגלו אחת. yachol la’amod al
raglo achat.
You say to yourself, "Look, if I were to take away that
stone and I were to take away or take away that pot,
if could the כהן Kohen still stand on one foot and do
the עבודה?" Avodah? Now again, it's not just "could you do this?"
like "could you do this and do this?" like "could you do
this and do the שחיטה?" shechita? You know, actually we're not talking
about שחיטה. shechita. "Do this and do the קבלת הדם." kabbalas hadam.
Right? You gotta have... you gotta be real in good shape. Okay,
okay. What? "Couldn't do the הלכה halacha on one..." You could.
You could. You'd have to jump. You'd have to hop. Now what
I always wonder about that also is that like when we say
"if I were to take it away", is it the way I
am distributing my weight right now? Because the way I'm distributing my
weight right now, I've got all my weight on the foot on
the stone, and if you were to take it away, I would
fall. But if you would allow me to prepare myself for it
and redistribute my weight, right? Presumably that would be okay too. Anyway,
in that case, עבודתו כשרה, Avodato keshera, it's kosher. Because then I
am not standing on... now that seems to be saying that it
only makes if I could technically do the עבודה. Avodah. הלכתית halachically
we haven't said otherwise. I'm allowed to do the עבודה Avodah standing
on one foot. Okay, you might have said, "Well, I don't know,
if you gotta be sanctified... וכי דרך שירות בכך? v’chi derech sheirus
bikach? If you gotta be sanctified by coming in contact with the
floor, maybe both feet have to be in contact with the floor.
But presumably that's what it's saying, that in principle you really are
allowed to do the עבודה Avodah on one foot. So that's another
reason when you stand on your own foot, it's okay, Michael, because
then clearly... although maybe not. I don't know. It's a good question.
If I were to remove the foot underneath would I be... yeah...
no, clearly... I don't know. I have to think that one through.
Anyway, ואם לאו, ve'im lav, if not, עבודה פסולה, avodah pesulah, it's
invalid.
Okay. Imagine like the you know, using the שטענדער, shtender, like, or
for the בימה, bimah, you know, shouldn't lean on the בימה, bimah,
it's like a שטיק.
shtick. Right, well we actually, we actually borrow this הלכה halacha for
different areas in which you need to be standing, as we actually
say, if you're, if you're resting on something but you could stand
were you to take it away, then that's the right. So we
actually do use this הלכה halacha in other places. That is correct.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. בעי רבי אמי, Ba'ei Rabbi Ami, Rabbi Ami asked: נדלדלה אבן.
Nidaldelah even. Now let's say one of the stones of the floor
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you know, got loosened and it's
now technically it's no longer really cemented in. You could lift it
up and remove it. In practice, it's sitting there in the in
the same old place, but in but you know, but in principle,
it's not actually cemented in. Okay. So, ועמד עליה, ve'amad aleha, and
you stood on it, מהו, mahu, what's the הלכה? halacha? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: היכא דאין דעתו לחברה, Heicha de'ein da'ato
lechabrah, לא תיבעי לך. lo tiba'ei lach. If your plan is not
to re-cement it, you're going to remove it and replace it, then
there's no question. דודאי חוצץ, Devadai chotzetz, it's definitely seen as something
external. Okay, you're the plan the way you're treating it is a
piece that has to be removed. Okay. כי תיבעי לך דדעתו לחברה.
Ki tiba'ei lach deda'ato lechabrah. The question is is that they're planning
on bringing in the, you know, contractor and he's going to pour
put in the cement or whatever he's going to do and re-attach
it. So מאי, mai, what do we say? כיון דדעתו לחברה כמאן
דמחברה דמיא. Keivan deda'ato lechabrah keman demachabrah damya. So therefore, it's seen
as as good as done, right, you know, because it's in the
right place, it just has to be attached, so maybe that is
enough to make it seem as part of the floor. We actually
you have interesting הלכות halachos when is something part of the floor,
if you scatter hay for a סוכה, sukkah, whatever, to make it
less than twenty אמות, amos, if your דעת da'at is to be
מבטל mevatel the hay there and so on. Although there there's not
maybe as much of a formal definition. Here there's a הלכה halacha
that it has to be anyway attached. But nevertheless, that's seen as
now it's part of the floor. או דילמא השתא מיהא תלישא, O
dilma hashta miha telishah, or do we say now, it doesn't matter,
right now it is not attached and it's considered to be not
part of the floor.
What if that rock or whatever it is was missing altogether, then
like you're actually stepping on the...
That's the next case of the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. רבה זוטא בעי,
Rabba Zuta ba'ei, the minor Rabba, I don't know who that was,
asked, בעי להכי, ba'ei lehachi, he asked the following way: בעי רבי
אמי, Ba'ei Rabbi Ami, Rabbi Ami asked: נקרה
אבן. Nikrah even. That stone was removed from the setting in which
it was placed and now there's a little bit of a hole
in the ground.
Okay. ועמד במקומה, Ve'amad bimkomah, and you did the עבודה avodah standing
in that little in that, you know, indent, okay, in that hole.
מהו, mahu, what's the הלכה? halacha? You're still standing on the dirt
of הר הבית Har Habayis of the עזרה. azarah. Somebody closer to
הר הבית. Har Habayis. Exactly. מאי קמיבעיא ליה, Mai kamiba'aya lei, what's
the question? Here's the question: כי קדיש דוד רצפה. Ki kadish David
ritzpah. We're going to assume that David, although Shlomo obviously was the
one who constructed the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but you know, we're
going to the גמרא Gemara assumes that David was the one who,
you know, not only sort of identified the place but actually did
the ritual required to sanctify the place. So that the sanctification of
the grounds of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was done by David.
Okay. So when David sanctified the floor, כי קדיש דוד רצפה עליונה
קדיש, Ki kadish David ritzpah elyona kadish, only the upper floor, the
upper level, which is interesting because the stones hadn't even been there,
but I don't know, so I don't know what the גמרא Gemara
means. Does the גמרא Gemara mean that he laid the stones and
he sanctified the stones? Does it mean the first inch of soil
as opposed to the deeper parts? I don't know exactly the רצפה,
ritzpah, okay, because רצפה ritzpah suggests the constructed floor, not just the
ground. So how do you construct, how do you sanctify a רצפה
ritzpah that isn't there? It's sounding like it assumes that he maybe
built the רצפה. ritzpah. Okay. או דילמא, O dilma, or do we
say, עד ארעא דתהומא קדיש. ad ar'ah detehoma kadish. He sanctified all
the dirt underneath and any of the use of the dirt underneath
also is the floor of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and a
floor that is not paved or whatever still counts as a floor
of a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, okay. Who said it needed to
be paved? So the גמרא Gemara says: ותיבעי לך כל עזרה כולה.
Vetiba'ei lach kol azarah kullah. So if that's your question, why do
you ask about one stone? What you should ask is a simpler
question. Let's say all of the stones got stripped away and you're
just standing on the dirt. Right? Why do you ask this funny
question about you're standing in a hole?
The real question is because it's more likely that like a stone
would get...
All right. Okay. But that's the גמרא's Gemara question. It sounds like
there's something about the fact that it's not like the other the
other rest of the floor. Whereas what your question has nothing to
do with whether it's like the rest of the floor or not,
it just has to do with what's the story below the stones.
Okay. So לעולם, le'olam, the גמרא Gemara says, פשיטא ליה דעד ארעא
דתהומא קדיש. peshita lei dead ar'ah detehoma kadish. You're right. It this
you know, Rabbi Ami or whoever it was, Rabbi Ami assumed that
the dirt also was sanctified. And if you stripped away the stones
and you did it on the dirt, it would also work. והכי
קמיבעיא ליה, Vehachi kamiba'aya lei, here's his question: דרך שירות בכך או
אין דרך שירות בכך. Derech sheirut bekach o ein derech sheirut bekach.
If you're standing in a hole, okay, you're not at level at
the ground level, you're standing in a hole, is that considered דרך
שירות? derech sheirut? תיקו, Teiku, and the גמרא Gemara does not know
the answer. Well standing on one foot or... So right, it brings
back the answer of the standing on one foot. So but what
I wonder about the standing on one foot is, I actually have
to see, you know, if this gets discussed, but you could sort
of say, if you act this would be funny if this were
true, but we could we could hypothesize that if you're standing on
one foot and doing it, you know, I can't even do it,
I'm just anyway, you're doing it, that's not דרך שירות. derech sheirut.
But if you're standing on two feet, it is דרך שירות. derech
sheirut. Ah, there's a problem that it's not defined as standing on
the ground, because one foot isn't directly on the ground, right, if
one is on a rock? No, since you could support all of
yourself with that foot that's on the ground, halachically you're defined as
standing directly on the ground, because you could stand directly on the
ground, you don't need the other foot. But because you're not standing
on one foot, it's דרך חירות, derech cheirus, right? It would be
an interesting way to balance it, to say to do it on
one foot would be invalid because it's not דרך חירות. derech cheirus.
To do it both feet on the whatever, but to do it
one foot on the ground and one foot on the stone, if
in theory you could balance yourself, then you're not defined as standing
on the stone and because both feet are planted, it is דרך
חירות. derech cheirus. So that would be interesting. Okay, but anyway, bottom
line is, yes.
As opposed to standing on a missing part of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash floor, which is not דרך חירות derech cheirus at all
potentially.
Right, or the גמרא Gemara seems to be because you're deep in
a hole, right, if it just was like an inch lower or
something I don't think that would be the case, I think it's
because you're deep in a hole. Okay, anyway, but that's the point.
You have to be directly standing on the floor, interesting question when
one foot is on and one foot is off, which gets used
in other areas of הלכה, halacha, somebody's leaning on a cane, other
types of questions about places where we want we require or prefer
that a person be standing, you know, what is considered standing? Getting
an עליה aliyah or something? Getting an עליה, aliyah, other types of
questions or whatever. Anyway, but a lot of those things are not
מעכב בדיעבד. meakev b'di'eved.
Anyway, you know, but certainly לכתחילה lechatchilah how do you have to
position yourself, try to position yourself. Okay, so that's the question about
what's you know about the definition of standing, and then this other
issue about and your feet directly on the ground, the way the
ground and the כלי שרת klei shares sanctify the כהן. kohen. And
then this last question about דרך—you derech know, which part of the
ground is sanctified and דרך חירות. derech cheirus. Yes.
And just so I love the deep, was there a story about
David?
Yeah, there was a yeah, there was a
set on this spot here in
at the—no, that was where he was doing the מזבח, mizbeach, but
yes, there was a story when David was sanctifying and he dug
too far and whatever the תהום tehom all that גמרא Gemara at
the end of סוכה, Sukkah, that's correct. Okay, now we get to
the
גמרא Gemara about—for lefties. קיבול בשמאל—not kibul b'smol about lefties actually, about—I'm
a lefty—using your left hand. Okay, so קיבול בשמאל פסול, kibul b'smol
pasul, רבי שמעון מכשיר. Rabbi Shimon machshir. If you accepted with the
left it's invalid, the קבלה, kabbalah, all the עבודות, avodas, but the
משנה Mishnah mentions the קבלה, kabbalah, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
actually the קבלה kabbalah you could do with your left hand. So
he's not saying any עבודה avodah you could do with your left
hand, specifically the קבלה. kabbalah. So we're going to see why. תנו
רבנן: Tnu rabanan: באצבע. b'etzba. So the פסוק pasuk here says ולקח
הכהן
מדם החטאת באצבעו ונתן.
v'lakach hakohen
m'dam hachattas b'etzbao v'natan. Okay, so
ולקח v'lakach we're going to say
is קבלה kabbalah and ונתן v'natan
is
obviously—oh,
והזה. v'hiza. Okay, so ולקח v'lakach we're going to say is קבלה
kabbalah and והזה v'hiza is obviously זריקה. zerikah.
Okay? And the keyword here is
באצבעו, b'etzbao, because we're going to say later that the word אצבע
etzba based on the what the תורה Torah says by the מצורע
metzora when it says אצבעו הימנית etzbao hayemanis etc. that אצבע etzba
means ימין, yamin, okay, the right—the right hand.
So חז"ל—the chazal תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is going to read that
the word באצבעו etzbao goes on both. ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת באצבעו,
v'lakach hakohen mi-dam hachattas b'etzbao, באצבעו והזה. b'etzbao v'hiza.
He has to do the קבלה kabbalah with the right hand, I
mean not with the finger literally but with the right hand, and
he has to use the right finger to do the sprinkling. So
that's how they're going to learn both קבלה kabbalah and זריקה zerikah
have to be with the ימין. yamin. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
going to say no, it's just באצבעו והזה. b'etzbao v'hiza. The sprinkling
is with the right hand but not the קבלה. kabbalah. He's only
going to read the word באצבעו etzbao to go on the second
part of the פסוק. pasuk. Let's see why. Okay. תנו
רבנן: Tnu rabanan: באצבעו ולקח, b'etzbao v'lakach, I mean—ולקח באצבעו, v'lakach b'etzbao,
מלמד
שלא תהא קבלה אלא בימין, melamed shelo t'hei kabbalah ela b'yamin, the
catching of the blood is only with the right hand. באצבעו ונתן,
b'etzbao v'natan, מלמד
שלא תהא נתינה אלא בימין. melamed shelo t'hei netinah ela b'yamin. That's
the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. That both have to be with the
right hand. אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, says רבי שמעון: Rabbi
Shimon: וכי נאמר יד בקבלה? v'chi ne'emar yad b'kabbalah? Does it say
the word יד yad by catching the blood? לא נאמר
אלא באצבעו ונתן. lo ne'emar ela b'etzbao v'natan. It only says the
word אצבע etzba so therefore באצבעו ונתן. b'etzbao v'natan. Oh, not והזה,
v'hiza, excuse me, ha, my mistake. ונתן
על קרנות המזבח, v'natan al karnos hamizbeach, right, I—my apologies. Okay. ונתן
על קרנות המזבח. v'natan al karnos hamizbeach. All right, so it says
באצבעו ונתן. b'etzbao v'natan. Okay, so only—וכי נאמר יד בקבלה אלא
באצבעו ונתן,
v'chi ne'emar yad b'kabbalah
ela b'etzbao v'natan, שלא תהא נתינה אלא בימין. shelo t'hei netinah ela
b'yamin. הא לא נאמר יד
בקבלה, ha lo ne'emar yad b'kabbalah, since it doesn't say יד, yad,
קיבול בשמאל כשר. kibul b'smol kasher. With your left hand it's okay.
Now the question is what is—the heck is he talking about about
the word יד? yad? Clearly באצבעו ונתן b'etzbao v'natan he's reading to
mean אצבע etzba means the right. באצבעו ונתן. b'etzbao v'natan. So
therefore—so who needs So the word יד. yad. What he really wants
to say is you only read this word connected with the second
part of the פסוק, pasuk, not with the first part of the
פסוק, pasuk, right? But what does why does he say oh since
it didn't say the word יד, yad, we know that it's not
referring you know that the קבלה kabbalah doesn't have to be with
the left hand, doesn't have to be with the right hand. What
the heck are you talking about? You're implicitly agreeing that the word
אצבע etzba means the right, and that's how you're saying באצבעו ונתן
be-etzbao ve-natan means that the זריקה zrikah has to be with the
right. So why are you refusing to read it backwards? Even if
your principle was you only read this forwards and not backwards, why
are you mentioning whether the verse says the word hand or not?
It's not about the verse saying the word hand. It's about the
fact that you're reading this with the second half of the verse
and not the first half of the verse. Okay, so you you
think you have an answer Gloria? No. I have a more
basic question.
Yeah, go for it.
Why does אצבע etzba mean right hand?
Oh so that we're going to learn from a גזירה שוה gezerah
shavah by the מצורע. metzora. By the מצורע metzora it speaks about
אצבעו הימנית etzbao ha-yemanit and so on. So based on we haven't
said that yet, that's taken for granted, we will say it soon,
but based on a גזירה שוה gezerah shavah with מצורע metzora we're
going to learn that the word אצבע etzba in the context of
the עבודה avodah always means right, okay. All right, so the גמרא
gemara says like this. Now the גמרא gemara says like this. רב
שמעון ממה נפשך. Reb Shimon mi-man nafshach. Now רב שמעון Reb Shimon
let's for
either way you're going let's figure this out. אי איתא i issei
גזירה שוה, gezerah shavah, if you hold of the גזירה שוה gezerah
shavah of the word אצבע etzba and יד yad to mean right
hand, which is implicit here, we haven't spelled it out, so כי
לא נאמר יד בקבלה מאי הוי? ki lo ne'emar yad be-kabbalah mai
hava? So what if it doesn't say the word יד? yad?
Who cares? It says the word אצבע etzba and אצבע etzba means
the right. Not only that, you implicitly agree the word אצבע etzba
means the right because that's how you know that the זריקה zrikah
has to be with the right hand. ואי ליתא ve-i leise גזירה
שוה, gezerah shavah, and
and number two,
ואי ליתא ve-i leise גזירה שוה gezerah shavah if the word אצבע
etzba doesn't mean right, so כי נאמר יד בקבלה מאי הוי? ki
ne'emar yad be-kabbalah mai hava? So יד yad also wouldn't mean right.
Meaning it's not like he's saying oh the word יד, yad, that
I would agree would mean the right hand, but it doesn't say
יד yad it only says the word אצבע. etzba. First of all,
says the גמרא, gemara, we always learn them in a packet. So
either you're going to say both the word יד yad and אצבע
etzba mean right or they both don't mean right. Okay, number you
know, so like what the heck are you talking about? And not
only that implicitly you agree that the word אצבע etzba means right
because that's how you learn that the זריקה zrikah has to be
with the right hand. So אמר רב יהודה amar rav yehuda לעולם
ליתא le'olam leise גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah. He doesn't hold of it.
אצבע etzba doesn't mean right and יד yad doesn't mean right. Okay.
והכי קאמר. ve-hachi ka'amar. וכי נאמר יד ימין בקבלה? ve-chi ne'emar yad
yamin be-kabbalah?
Neither יד yad nor אצבע etzba would mean right. And what רב
שמעון Reb Shimon is really saying is the verse never says you
need your right hand. וכי ve-chi okay, so ולא נאמר יד ימין
בקבלה ve-lo ne'emar yad yamin be-kabbalah כיון דלא נאמר יד ימין בקבלה
ke-be-smol hava ve-lo ne'emar yad yamin be-kabbalah קיבלו בשמאל כשר. kibblo bi-smol
kasher. What רב שמעון Reb Shimon is saying is I reject the
whole idea that any word by itself means right. If it wanted
to say right it would have said the right hand. It would
have so if it didn't say right hand you can't learn that
you need a right hand for anything. Of course the problem with
that is and why do you need a right hand for why
do you agree that you need a right hand for throwing of
the blood? So אמר ליה רבה amar lei rabba אי הכי i-hachi
אפילו נתינה נמי. afilu netinah nami. The placing of the blood on
the corners also shouldn't require the right hand. Okay.
ועוד ve-od and number two וכי לית ליה לרב שמעון ve-chi leise
lei le-reb shimon גזירה שוה? gezerah shavah? You're telling me רב שמעון
Reb Shimon doesn't hold of the word that you know אצבע etzba
וימין ve-yamin means the right hand? I'll show you a ברייתא baraita
that he says it black on white. ותניא ve-tanya רב שמעון אומר
Reb Shimon omer כל מקום שנאמר יד אינו אלא ימין. kol makom
she-ne'emar yad ein ela yamin. When it says the word יד yad
it means right hand, that's good, that's what was implicit in his
earlier statement, but then he goes on also אצבע אינו אלא ימין.
etzba ein ela yamin. אצבע etzba means the right hand. So don't
tell me that the problem of רב שמעון Reb Shimon is whether
the word אצבע etzba means right hand or not. רב שמעון Reb
Shimon is explicit. יד yad means right, אצבע etzba means right. It's
implicit here because that's what רבה Rabba says באצבעו ונתן be-etzbao ve-natan
is telling you that the נתינה netinah that the נתינה netinah has
to be with the right hand. So once this means right which
we know in general רב שמעון Reb Shimon says and it's implicit
here that it means right, why is he saying that the קבלה
kabbalah does not have to be in the right hand? And why
does he mention the fact that the תורה torah doesn't use the
word hand? What did it have to do with the תורה torah
using the word hand? It should just say the word אצבע etzba
goes in the second half of the פסוק pasuk not the first.
So רבה Rabba has a great read of רב שמעון. Reb Shimon.
So here's what רבא Rava says. אלא אמר רבא ella amar rava
לעולם אית ליה le'olam islei גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah. רב שמעון Reb
Shimon holds of the גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah.
אצבע etzba means right, ימין yamin means right, יד yad means right,
אצבע etzba means right. והכי קאמר ve-hachi ka'amar here's what he says.
וכי נאמר יד בקבלה? ve-chi ne'emar yad be-kabbalah?
Does the word say יד? yad? It doesn't. הוה ולא נאמר יד
בקבלה אלא אצבע hava ve-lo ne'emar yad be-kabbalah ela etzba since it
says the word אצבע etzba ואי אפשר לקבלה באצבע ve-i efshar le-kabbalah
be-etzba try catching the blood with your finger. Okay, try holding the
bowl with your finger.
So therefore קיבלו בשמאל כשר. kibblo bi-smol kasher. So what he says
is a very simple point. He's just explaining why am I reading
באצבעו ונתן be-etzbao ve-natan and not ולקח באצבעו? ve-lakach be-etzbao? And he's
saying because you if it said hand I would have said the
word... Is referring to the catching of the blood, because you catch
with your hands holding the vessel. But because it says the word
אצבע, etzba, you can't catch, you can't hold the vessel with your
finger. So therefore רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says, obviously the פסוק pasuk
reads ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת באצבעו ונתן על קרנות המזבח. Velakach hakohen
midam hachatat b'etzba'o venatan al karnot hamizbeach. Okay? Yes, אצבע etzba means
right and יד yad means right, etc. But because it's using the
word אצבע, etzba, the only act it could be referring to is
the placing of the blood, not the catching of the blood. Very
reasonable read of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay? So that's great פשט pshat
in רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. But now the גמרא Gemara challenges it.
Now the
גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה רב סמא בריה דרב אשי לרבינא. Amar
lei Rav Sama berei d'Rav Ashi l'Ravina. רב סמא Rav Sama said
to רבינא: Ravina: אפשר דעביד ליה אוזן לשפת מזרק ומקבל. Efshar d'avid
lei ozen l'sfat mizrak umkabel. I don't understand, you never heard of
a vessel you get a little like an אוזן ozen to a
vessel? You get one of those things where yes, there are vessels—you
can hold things like you know those little gravy boats, you know,
you hold with your finger and you can support the whole vessel.
So why not? I'll show you a way that you can actually
catch the blood just with your finger. Make an אוזן ozen to
the vessel, flip your finger through it
and catch the blood just holding on to the vessel with your
finger. Okay? So that can't be what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon means.
Now just because he's got a קשיא kasha does not mean that
it's not what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon meant. רבא Rava is still
a great reader of רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
is saying give me a break, the word אצבע etzba refers to
the act of placing, not the act of catching. But the גמרא
Gemara is saying no, in theory that would not have been a
good argument so that can't be what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon means.
Okay, אלא אמר אביי. Ella amar Abaye. So אביי Abaye ignores to
make a better פשט pshat of רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, אביי Abaye
ignores the fact that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon focused on the word
אצבע etzba versus the word of יד, yad, right? That was רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon's point. It says אצבע etzba doesn't say יד. yad.
אביי Abaye says ignore that, that's not what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
is talking about at all. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is just making
a simpler point. במקרא נדרש לפניו ולאחריו קמיפלגי. Bemikra nidrash lefanav ule'acharav
kamiflegi. The simple question is that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says
we read the word אצבע etzba both ways. We read it like
this and we read it like that. It's נדרש לפניו
ולאחריו.
nidrash lefanav
ule'acharav. So it refers both to the catching of the blood and
to the placing of the blood. And רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says
no, it only refers to the next part. It's only, okay, it's
only באצבעו ונתן. b'etzba'o venatan. It only applies to the putting of
the blood, not to the catching. Obviously that's not grammatically, grammatically ולקח
הכהן מדם החטאת באצבעו Velakach hakohen midam hachatat b'etzba'o comma. Okay, you
wouldn't say באצבעו ונתן. b'etzba'o venatan. But anyway, so that's the debate,
it has nothing to do with the use of the word אצבע
etzba versus the use of the word יד. yad. The תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma just says we read this word באצבעו b'etzba'o for the
first half and the second half, and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says
we only read it for the second half. Okay. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. Said אביי: Abaye: הא דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון.
Ha d'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar the son of
רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. מפקא מדי אבוה. Mafka midei avua. He is
excluded from his father, meaning רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון'ס Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi
Shimon's position both rejects the position of his father ומפקא מדרבנן umafka
miderabbanan and it rejects the position of the רבנן. Rabbis. He stakes
out a third position which is neither his father's position or the
תנא קמא'ס Tanna Kamma's position. דתניא: Detanya: רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר
כל מקום שנאמר אצבע בקבלה
שינה בקבלה פסול בנתינה כשר. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon omer kol makom
shene'emar etzba bekabbalah shina bekabbalah pasul binetinah kasher. So if it said
the word אצבע etzba by the קבלה kabbalah of the blood, then
I would say
that if you altered the קבלה, kabbalah, you did it with your
left hand, you invalidated it, but the נתינה netinah could be with
your left hand and still be כשר. kasher. So basically what he's
saying, it's a complicated way of saying it, but basically what רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon is saying is since you
really here have three options of the באצבעו. b'etzba'o. It could be
referring to earlier and later, which is the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
you require it by both. It could be referring only to later,
which is רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, you require it only by the
נתינה. netinah. And what's your third option?
Just the first one, which is the פשט pshat of the read
of the פסוק. pasuk. So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi
Shimon is saying you only need to use your right hand for
the קבלה, kabbalah, not for the זריקה. zrikah. The mirror image of
his father. Okay. So since it says באצבעו b'etzba'o by the לקיחה,
lekichah, if you use the לקיחה lekichah with your left hand you
invalidated it, but the נתינה netinah with your left hand you did
not invalidate. Okay.
So the רבנן Rabbanan say you need it for קבלה kabbalah
and
זריקה—well zrikah not זריקה, zrikah, let's do נתינה, netinah, we'll get to
זריקה zrikah later because
there might be a difference there coming up. Talk about a חטאת.
chatas. Okay. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you need it for נתינה.
netinah. And רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon says you
need it for קבלה. kabbalah. So that's why he's neither his father
nor the רבנן. Rabbanan. He reads this פסוק pasuk only the first
half, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon reads the פסוק pasuk only the second
half, and the רבנן Rabbis read it both ways. Okay. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מפקא מדרבנן דתניא רבי
אלעזר ברבי
שמעון. Mafka miderabbanan detanya Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. Rabbi Shimon says: כל מקום שנאמר אצבע וקבלה, kol
makom she'ne'emar etzba v'kabbalah,
and it says אצבע etzba by the catching, which is our פסוק,
pasuk, שינה בקבלה פסול—there shina b'kabbalah pasul if you changed it and
did your left hand you invalidated it. בנתינה כשר—but B'netinah kasher if
you did the placing of the blood with your left hand it
would be okay. וכל מקום שנאמר אצבע מנתינה, v'chol makom she'ne'emar etzba
minetinah, but there's places where it's the opposite. There's places where it
only requires the אצבע, etzba, the right hand, on the
placing, okay, and not on the catching, like my father said. There's
cases that that's true. And in those cases, שינה בנתינה פסול ובקבלה
כשר, shina b'netinah pasul u'v'kabbalah kasher, then it would be the flip:
if you would do the placing with your left hand you'd invalidate
it, if you do the catching with your left hand it would
be okay. So Rabbi Eleazar bar Rabbi Shimon is fascinating that he
doesn't sort of make it an across the board. Sometimes it's this
way, sometimes it's that way, you have to look at the way
that the Torah phrases it each time. His general rule is you
need it by
קבלה. kabbalah. Where's the case that you need it by נתינה? netinah?
והיכן נאמר אצבע בנתינה? v'heichan ne'emar etzba b'netinah? Where do you need
it just by the נתינה? netinah? דכתיב, Dechtiv, it says, and this
is by a specific חטאת, chatat, this is by the פר par
by the מלואים: miluim: ולקחת מדם הפר ונתת על קרנות המזבח באצבעך.
v'lakachta midam hapar v'natatah al karnot hamizbeach b'etzbe'echa. So there, there's no
question, right? The word באצבעך b'etzbe'echa there comes after the word ונתת.
v'natatah.
You got that? Okay, you see how that is? So this is,
this is a specific one case. By the פר המילואים par hamiluim
it says: ולקח
מדם הפר
ונתן על קרנות
המזבח
באצבעך.
v'lakach midam hapar v'natan
al karnot hamizbeach
b'etzbe'echa. So in that case he says this word באצבעך b'etzbe'echa is
going to go on the ונתן, v'natan, but it is not going
to go too back on the ולקח. v'lakach. So this will be
a case that Rabbi Eleazar bar Rabbi Shimon will say you need
it for the placing and not for the catching. But the general
rule is you need it for the catching and not for the
placing. But here there's no other way to read the פסוק. pasuk.
The word באצבעך b'etzbe'echa goes on the word placing and not on
the word catching. And therefore says the גמרא: Gemara: וקסבר רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון v'kasavar Rabbi Eleazar bar Rabbi Shimon holds מקרא נדרש לפניו.
mikra nidrash lefanav.
The verse is read to the one immediately
previous. באצבעך b'etzbe'echa goes to the word ונתן, v'natan,
okay, ולא לפני פניו, v'lo lifnei fanav, it doesn't go two back,
it doesn't go to the word ולקח v'lakach in this פסוק pasuk
by the פר מלואים. par miluim. It only goes to the word
ונתן, v'natan, and also ולא לאחריו. v'lo l'acharav.
Okay, Rabbi Eleazar bar Rabbi Shimon says באצבעו b'etzbe'o here goes on
the word ולקח v'lakach and it doesn't go on the next part
of the word, it doesn't go on the word נתן. natan. So
for Rabbi Eleazar bar Rabbi Shimon, the word only goes to the
previous part of the פסוק pasuk and only the immediately previous. Okay,
and that's why by the פר מלואים par miluim only the נתינה
netinah has to be with the right hand, not the לקיחה, lekichah,
and that's why getting back to our, because that's two previous, the
לקיחה, lekichah, and why getting back to our פסוק, pasuk, he says
the opposite of his father. His father reads the word אצבע etzba
on the second half of the פסוק: pasuk: the נתינה netinah has
to be with the right hand. He reads it on the first
half of the פסוק, pasuk, which is more grammatical, but that's only
the catching has to be with the right hand, not the placing.
Okay? Different ways to read it. At the end of the day,
the key is that the word אצבע etzba means ימין. yamin. This
פסוק pasuk refers to both עבודות, avodot, and there are three possibilities
of which one you interpret the word אצבע etzba about: both, just
the placing, just the קבלה. kabbalah. Rabbi Eleazar bar Rabbi Shimon I
gotta tell you is the most fascinating
because, besides that he makes every case separate, distinct, okay, is that
the fact is that he gives greater weight to the קבלה kabbalah
than the placing of the blood on the מזבח. mizbeach. If anything,
logic, if you had to pick the two, this is—you would assume
is the much more significant one, okay. Although again, remember the catching
of the blood in the כלי שרת keli sharet is part of
the sanctifying of the blood, so maybe it's somehow connected as a
result of that. How do we פסקינן? paskinan? You back to your
מי כעמך ישראל Mi K'Amcha Yisrael role, I assume we פוסקים poskim
like the רבנן. rabbanan. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara.
Yeah, this sure, absolutely. But let's also be honest: פשט pshat of
the word ולקח v'lakach is not the catching of the blood. Part
of the word ולקח v'lakach is you dip your finger in the
blood, and that's why you use your finger to do the לקיחה.
lekichah. The רבנן rabbanan use the word ולקח v'lakach to refer to
the catching of the blood. Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbah bar bar Chanah amar Rabbi Yochanan: כל מקום
שנאמר אצבע וכהונה. kol makom she'ne'emar etzba u'kehunah.
Now we're going to sort of get to the דרשה derasha that
we were suggesting before. Wherever it says
אצבע etzba and/or כהונה, kehunah, we'll see that in a minute, okay,
אינה אלא ימין. einah ela yamin. So we're not mentioning יד yad
now, יד yad we mentioned before, but anyway finger or כהן kohen
means you have to use the right hand, the right finger, you
have to use the right. Okay. Now קסלקא דעתך, kasalka daitach, we're
assuming, says the גמרא, Gemara, תרתי בעינן, tarti ba'inan, that the ו
vov here means and, that the verse has to both say כהן
באצבעו kohen b'etzbe'o or something like that. And when it says כהן
kohen and אצבע, etzba, so it's like then it means the right
hand or the right finger of the כהן. kohen. One of those
would not mean it. כדכתיב ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת באצבעו, k'dichtiv v'lakach
hacohen midam hachatat b'etzbe'o, okay, מדם החטאת. midam hachatat. I think this
is our פסוק, pasuk, I just wrote it up here. Okay, מדם
החטאת. midam hachatat. So you have the word, so let's get this
rid of these now.
Okay, now we're going to focus on, how do we know it
means ימין? yamin? So this פסוק pasuk has both. Now we don't
know it means ימין, yamin, but it does have two the two
key words. Okay, and we're going to learn it from connecting it
to the מצורע, metzora, because what does it say by the מצורע?
metzora? Because it says by the מצורע, metzora, רש״י Rashi quotes the
פסוק. pasuk. It says
well I know רש״י Rashi doesn't quote the whole פסוק pasuk anyway,
but it says ולקח הכהן את הדם באצבעו הימנית ונתן על תנוך
אזן הימנית velakach hacohen et hadam b'etzba'o hayemanit venatan al tenuch ozen
hayemanit etc. So by the by the מצורע metzora it says כהן
kohen and and אצבע etzba and ימין. yamin. So here כהן kohen
and אצבע etzba means ימין. yamin. If you want me to see
let me quickly see a court the פסוק pasuk since it is
14:25.
14:25?
Yes. It's not it's not the beginning of 14 in ויקרא. Vayikra.
Hold on.
Hold on. It says ולקח הכהן מן
האשם ונתן על תנוך אזן המטהר הימנית ועל בהן ידו הימנית ועל
בהן רגלו הימנית.
velakach hacohen min
ha'asham venatan al tenuch ozen hamitaher hayemanit veal bohen yado hayemanit veal
bohen raglo hayemanit. וטבל הכהן את
אצבעו הימנית מן השמן אשר על כפו השמאלית
והזה מן השמן באצבעו.
vetaval hacohen et etzba'o hayemanit min
hashemen
asher al kapo hasmilit vehizah min
hashemen b'etzba'o.
Okay, וטבל הכהן
את אצבעו הימנית.
vetaval
hacohen et etzba'o hayemanit.
That's by the מצורע. metzora. That's 14 14:16. 14:16. Okay, וטבל הכהן
vetaval hacohen
what was it? וטבל הכהן vetaval hacohen dot dot dot dot dot
dot את
אצבעו
הימנית. et etzba'o hayemanit. את אצבעו הימנית.
et etzba'o
hayemanit.
Okay, so that's by the מצורע. metzora. That's 14. Okay. Anyway, so
you have the word כהן kohen and אצבע etzba and ימין. yamin.
So now do we learn out that you if you say both
it means ימין yamin or either it means ימין? yamin? So at
this stage says the גמרא Gemara we're assuming that you needed to
say both to mean right. Okay.
Oh my god, it's the next line in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
Just shows you how tired I was when I was preparing the
גמרא. Gemara. קסלקא דעתך תרתי בעינן כדכתיב ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת באצבעו
וילפינן ממצורע דכתיב וטבל הכהן את אצבעו הימנית kasalka da'atach tarti be'inan
kidechsiv velakach hacohen midam hachatat b'etzba'o veyalpinnan mimmetzora dechsiv vetaval hacohen et
etzba'o hayemanit יישר כוח. yashar koach. Wonderful. Next פסוק. pasuk. All right.
והרי ve-harei now והרי ve-harei so assuming you need both to mean
right. והרי קמיצה ve-harei kemitzah
how about the taking of the מנחה minchah with your hand breadth?
Okay. דלא כתיב ביה אלא כהונה. dela ksiv beih ela kehunah. It
only says the word כהן. kohen. It says okay וקמץ הכהן vekamatz
hacohen because you don't use your finger. You use you know multiple
fingers. So it only mentions כהן. kohen. ותנן vesnan קמץ בשמאל פסול.
kamaz b'smol pasul.
Okay, that if you used your left hand it's invalid. So you
see that it doesn't have to say the word אצבע. etzba. אלא
אמר רבא ela amar Rava says רבא Rava או אצבע או כהונה.
o etzba o kehunah. Fine. One or the other means the right
hand. So now we had to broaden that it means one or
the other in order to include the idea of the קמיצה kemitzah
forced us to say that the word כהן kohen is enough. Now
we're going to have a real problem because it says כהן kohen
a lot. Okay, and now you're going to tell me that every
time it says כהן kohen it means the right hand. So let's
אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye said אביי Abaye הרי הולכת איברים
לכבש harei holachat evarim lakevesh how about bringing of the limbs of
the sacrifice to the ramp? דכתיב בהו כהונה. dechsiv behu kehunah. There
it says the word כהן. kohen. דכתיב והקריב הכהן את הכל והקטיר
המזבחה. dechsiv vehikriv hacohen et hakol vehiktir hamizbeachah. You should all bring
it you know should bring it close and offer it. ואמר מר
זו הולכת איברים לכבש. ve'amar mar zo holachat evarim lakevesh. That's bringing
it to the ramp. ותנן vesnan and when the גמרא Gemara describes
how they would you know chop up the animal and different כהנים
kohanim would bring different parts of it. So it's when they you
know often a כהן kohen would have one thing in his right
hand one thing in his left hand. הרגל של ימין בשמאלו. haregel
shel yamin bismolo. The right leg of the foreleg of the animal
would be in the כהן's kohen's in the כהן's kohen's left hand.
He would have the the head in the right hand because that's
more important and the front leg in the left hand. ובית ערוה
לחוץ uveit ervah lachutz and you know the sort of the part
of the where the genitals are facing outside. That's not our
issue. Anyway, so you see there left is okay. Now that you've
expanded it says every time it says כהן kohen it means right.
So really? So how come here left is okay? So he says
no כי אמרינן או אצבע או כהונה ki amrinan o etzba o
kehunah when do I say that either word means your right hand?
בדבר המעכב כפרה. bidvar hame'akev kapparah. That's when it's a central עבודה.
avodah. Something that is necessary for the atonement. When it's like you
know the catching of the blood the throwing of the blood the
the קמיצה kemitzah the offering of the קומץ. kometz. Things that are
a central part of the atonement. דומיא דמצורע dumya demetzora like the
מצורע. metzora. Okay but the bringing of the limbs if you didn't
do it the sacrifice is still good. So therefore that's not a
problem. So we're still going to argue that כהן kohen by itself
means right but only when it's the central acts of the עבודה.
avodah. So let's see but the גמרא Gemara says one minute והרי
קבלה ve-harei kabbalah how about the catching of the blood? דכתיב בו
כהונה dechsiv bo kehunah ודבר המעכב בכפרה הוא. vedavar hame'akev bekapparah hu.
Catching the blood it says כהן kohen right? Remember the only issue
here was that the word אצבע etzba maybe went to the first
half maybe went to the second half. That was the whole debate.
But כהן kohen is clearly on the first half. So how could
anybody, how could רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say, if this is correct,
that you don't need your right hand by the catching of the
blood? It says כהן, kohen, the whole debate of רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon implies that it's all about the word אצבע. etzba. That the
word כהן kohen does not do the job. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says ודבר המעכב כפרה הוא ותנן קיבל בשמאל פסול רבי שמעון
מכשיר. vedavar ham'akev kaparah hu vetnan kibel bismol pasul Rebbi Shimon machshir.
And רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it's okay. So you see רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon the word כהן kohen is not enough. So the
גמרא Gemara says רבי שמעון תרתי בעי. Rebbi Shimon tarti baei. Yeah
fine. רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, you're right, needs both the word כהן
kohen and the word אצבע. etzba. But what we're saying is is
that for the rabbis one or another is enough. Okay. So because
we had to now expand the argument to say that כהן kohen
the word כהן kohen is enough, we're running into a lot of
problems. Okay. And therefore oh it's only enough when you're dealing with
דבר המעכב כפרה davar ham'akev kaparah central עבודות. avodos. As for the
rabbis it's enough, for not for רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. For the
rabbis the word כהן kohen is enough. Okay fine. Now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this:
מי בעא רבי שמעון תרתי Mi baei Rebbi Shimon tarti one minute.
Where do you see that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon really says that
you need both the word כהן kohen and the word אצבע? etzba?
והתניא רבי שמעון אומר כל מקום שנאמר יד אינו אלא ימין אצבע
אינו אלא ימין. vehatanya Rebbi Shimon omer kol makom shene'emar yad eino
ela yamin etzba eino ela yamin. So the word אצבע etzba by
itself means the right hand. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon doesn't need the
word כהן. kohen. So the גמרא Gemara says אצבע לא בעי כהונה
כהונה בעי אצבע. etzba lo baei kehuna kehuna baei etzba. Fine you're
right. For רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it's all about the word אצבע.
etzba. It's not the word כהן. kohen. If it says the word
כהן kohen it needs to still says אצבע. etzba. It says אצבע
etzba it doesn't need to say כהן. kohen. So basically what we're
saying is like this: For the rabbis either word is enough, okay,
and maybe that's how the rabbis learned that you have to also
do the catching with your right hand, either word is enough. For
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it's only the word אצבע etzba is enough.
And אצבע etzba here he says is the second half of the
פסוק. pasuk. So because we've now expanded this statement to say כהן
kohen by itself is enough, we've gotten into a lot of problems.
So we're saying is כהן kohen itself is enough only for the
rabbis. For רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it's not about the word כהן.
kohen. It's about the word אצבע. etzba. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: So if that's true ואלא כהן למה לי
ve'ela kohen lama li for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon why is the
פסוק pasuk saying the word כהן kohen if it's not teaching me
the idea of the right hand? So that's a different הלכה halacha
בכהונם. bekehunam. They have to be in their service meaning they have
to be wearing the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. All right. So where
are we right now? We are rather than just saying it's all
about the word אצבע etzba which seems to be what we had
been saying, we're saying it's about the word כהן kohen and אצבע
etzba but now we've actually shifted it to mean כהן kohen or
אצבע. etzba. So now and which has got us into a lot
of problems. So the claim is that's for the rabbis, for רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon it's all about the word אצבע, etzba, for the
rabbis it's כהן kohen or אצבע etzba either is enough when you're
dealing with things that are מעכב כפרה. me'akev kaparah. But now we
got a problem. הרי זריקה, harei zerika, how about the throwing of
the blood on the altar? דלא כתיב ביה אלא כהונה. delo ksiv
bei ela kehuna. It says like the again that's not something you
use your finger for, we're no longer dealing with a חטאת, chatas,
חטאת chatas is the individual finger what's placed on the corners. We're
dealing with the blood of the עולה olah let's say that's thrown
and it doesn't mention אצבע etzba but it mentions the כהן kohen
throws the blood. Okay.
ותנן זרק בשמאל פסול ולא פליגי רבי שמעון. vetnan zarak bismol pasul
velo pligi Rebbi Shimon. If you use your left hand it's invalid
and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon does not disagree. So you see even
for רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, why does רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon not
disagree by the זריקה? zerika? You just got through saying that for
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon it's all about the word אצבע. etzba. If
it's all about the word אצבע, etzba, right? Because if it was
about the word כהן kohen here you would require a כהן kohen
you would require the right hand for the קבלה. kabbalah. So if
it's all about the word אצבע, etzba, why does רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon say, you know, and the point is this could have been
asked even independent of our whole argument of כהן kohen and אצבע.
etzba. Why does רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say that you can't do
the זריקה zerika with your left hand? Since for רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon he focuses on the word אצבע, etzba, clearly כהן kohen is
not enough, why does רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon learn that the זריקה
zerika has to be with your right, okay? זריקה zerika should be
it doesn't say the word אצבע, etzba, how do you know the
זריקה zerika can't be with your left hand? So the גמרא Gemara
says ולא פליגי רבי שמעון אמר אביי פליגי בברייתא. velo pligi Rebbi
Shimon amar Abaye pligi bebraisa. You know what? רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
does disagree with that as well. דתניא קיבל בשמאל פסול רבי שמעון
מכשיר. detanya kibel bismol pasul Rebbi Shimon machshir. If you catch it
with the left it's invalid, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it's okay.
זרק בשמאל פסול רבי שמעון מכשיר. zarak bismol pasul Rebbi Shimon machshir.
And the זריקה, zerika, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon also says is okay
with the left. Okay so basically so this is now working out,
okay. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon goes by אצבע. etzba. So basically what
we have is the following is רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon goes by
the for him it's about the word אצבע. etzba.
And therefore what says the word אצבע? etzba? The only says the
word אצבע etzba is נתינה, netina, okay, by the חטאת, chatas, okay.
There it
says באצבעו באצבעו ונתן. be'etzba'o be'etzba'o venasan.
Okay. It does not say it by the word it does not
say it by the קבלה, kabbalah, okay. And by the עולה olah
also right if so there you get it by the נתינה netina
you get it by the קבלה kabbalah you don't get it because
the קבלה kabbalah it says it just says ולקח הכהן. velakach hakohen.
Okay I'm not sure I'm doing this rightly. So you don't I
mean whatever I'm not sure I'm doing a good chart here but
anyway. So it does not say it by there it does not
say the word אצבע etzba and similarly by the עולה. olah. And
by the זריקה, zerikah, right? It says וזרק הכהן, ve-zarak ha-kohen, okay,
וזרק הכהן. ve-zarak ha-kohen. So by none of these does it say
the word אצבע. etzba. Okay, maybe there's a better way to do
this. Okay, so here you have, this is the way to do
it, okay, anyway, so here you have the word by נתינה netinah
of the חטאת chatat אצבעו, etzbao, assuming we're going to read this
at the second half, not the first half of the פסוק. pasuk.
קבלה kabalah you have the word כהן kohen and זריקה zerikah of
an עולה olah you have the word כהן. kohen. So רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says you go by אצבע. etzba. So for רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, okay, who says you go by אצבע etzba and only
אצבע, etzba, he only requires the right hand by the נתינה. netinah.
For the rabbis who say you go either by the word אצבע
etzba or by the word כהן, kohen, they require the right hand
by all three of these. Okay, so that's how we're now explaining
the debate. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon goes by the word אצבע, etzba,
that's only by the placing of the blood of the חטאת. chatat.
Everything else it says כהן, kohen, you do not need the right
hand. And the rabbis say כהן kohen is enough to tell you
the right hand and that's why you need it by the קבלה,
kabalah, that's why you need it by the זריקה zerikah of the
דם dam of the עולה. olah. Okay, so that, so we'll end
with that here, we will pick up with this tomorrow.